<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>Alex Stephen</title>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/"/>
 <updated>2017-02-16T23:16:26-08:00</updated>
 <id>http://localhost:4000</id>
 <author>
   <name>Alex Stephen</name>
 </author>
 
 
 
 <entry>
   <title>It's another blog I'll never update</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/reboot/"/>
   <updated>2017-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/posts/reboot</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I swear, this is like the fourth or fifth blog I’ve ever made.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 
 
 <entry>
   <title>Guatemala</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/guatemala/"/>
   <updated>2015-03-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/posts/guatemala</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was ported over from my old blog. It’s probably a mess&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over Spring Break, I went on a volunteer trip to Guatemala with some of the coolest people. Here are my thoughts on the week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;expectations&quot;&gt;Expectations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I never felt like I was able to fully process my expectations for this trip. Part of this was just pre-trip stress (yay college!) and part of it was a fundemental lack of anything to compare this trip to. I had absolutely no idea what could’ve happened. Nonetheless, everybody around me was more than willing to fill me in with their ideas of what I should be expecting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My doctors kept emphasizing how deadly everything was. The street food was toxic. The water was cyanide from a tap. Killer mosquitos control the air and hepitaitis was basically inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My parents kept emphasizing how dangerous everything was. Pickpockets on every block. Every building would be like a Western saloon, filled to the brim with thugs. A land devoid of power, plumbing, privacy and protein.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The entire country seemed framed by these fears before I left. They are well-intentioned, to be sure. Most Westerners aren’t used to the bacteria in the water, for instance. Pick-pockets do love tourists because of our cash, easily accessible wallets, and refusal to look with our eyes and not our viewfinders. Infrastructure typically isn’t as well-developed in Central America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, because I had no expectations, I let these fears creep into the back of my mind.As the trip approached, I started to think of it as this kind of painful transient state. Something that has to be endured and then is remembered fondly in the company of good friends, WiFi and a glass of supermarket wine. To some extent, it was to be seven days of pain for a couple of good stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look back and I’m ashamed of that mentality. I’m immensely glad that everything I thought was proven so wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reality&quot;&gt;Reality&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2015/guatemala/antigua.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Picture of Antigua&quot; /&gt;
All of those fears were completely unfounded. Guatemala is an extraordinarily beautiful, peaceful place. The street food seemed fine (I ate a sandwich and I haven’t died yet), there weren’t any mosquitoes and I didn’t feel the need to obsessively guard my possessions (granted, I wasn’t being stupid either).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In reality, the country was absolutely beautiful. The skylines were adorned with majestic volcanoes on every side. The night sky was filled with these strange lights - I believe they’re called “stars”? I don’t really see them in the States. The cobbelstone roads were surrounded by quaint, Old World style buildings that all individually radiated warmth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We stayed in a beautiful little hotel in the town of Antigua. I’ve never seen a place that’s able to blend outdoor nature with indoor life. Open courtyards surrounded by the rooms of yourself and your neighbors- it’s a type of architechure that I don’t think could ever happen in America. We could’ve jumped into our next door neighbor’s living room if we really wanted to (in fact, somebody almost did. oops). It’s a level of trust that I just can’t seem to get over and a embrace of nature that warm weather enables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The food turned out to be anything but toxic. It was delicious. The freshest produce arranged into flavorful dishes of eggs, chicken, rice, beans, potatoes and so much more. I didn’t expect so much variety of food and I didn’t expect how much of a treat it all would be. We had three meals daily at our homestay and each one was a highlight of the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that did surprise me was the driving. I’ve never thought of driving as a particularly scary endeavor. Accidents do unfortunately occur, but there is a system in place that tries to minimize them. Guatemala didn’t feel like that. It felt like NASCAR with oncoming traffic and scooters for good measure. I can’t remember how many times I thought our driver was about to hit somebody and how many times I thought somebody was inching far too close to us. Even in the most populated areas, I don’t visibilty remember any stop lights. Every intersection turned into a negotiation with the people around us. It was this strange mixture of pseudo high-speed hostage negotation and Russian roulette.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;work&quot;&gt;Work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2015/guatemala/work1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Working, but there ain't much there&quot; /&gt;
There’s a false idea that volunteers are meant to rescue a community and galvanize its occupants into saving themselves. It’s a really easy trap to fall into when you know that you’re helping people who are “less privileged.” It’s definitely a trap that I fell into before the trip began.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reality couldn’t be any farther from that. We spent four of our seven days building two cinder-block houses for two amazing families. The work was exhausting. I’ve never moved, or even seen, so many cement blocks in my life. I’ve mixed and poured hundreds of gallons of cement. Turns out, cement is heavy. Also, the sound of a hatchet striking a cinder block is a harsh, volatile shriek that belongs in a Kubrickian horror movie. At first listen, this doesn’t sound enjoyable at all. But, it ended up being some of the most enjoyable and rewarding work I’ve ever done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The families and the masons were so much of the reason why. Even though we were volunteering, it never felt like we were providing charity. The wives were just as involved as we were. They were always ready to haul cinder blocks at a moment’s notice. One of them was even pregnant! Every day, they greeted us with a midday snack and a warm smile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The masons were such a great source of knowledge. They were incredibly knowledgeable about their trade and helped us through every step of the process. Despite our inexperience (and complete inability to do anything right), none of them seemed irritated at us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2015/guatemala/work2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Where did those walls come from?&quot; /&gt;
Overall, I feel like I was given so much more from this work than I possibly could have put in. I learned so much from the masons and befriended them all. I’m even friends with one on Facebook! The families were so kind and taught us all about generosity when you have so little.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;touristy-stuff&quot;&gt;Touristy Stuff&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout the week, we did a whole bunch of “touristy” things that I’d be remiss not to mention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;orphanage&quot;&gt;Orphanage&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2015/guatemala/orphanage.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;We're such a cute group&quot; /&gt; 
This isn’t touristy at all. Throughout the semester, we amassed eleven (!) suitcases worth of donations to bring to Guatemala. Many of them went to a local orphanage, where we spent a couple hours. It was a humbling experience. The kids were so thrilled for our donations. One little boy was so thrilled at the sight of new toothpaste, as he began to horde half-a-dozen boxes for safe keeping. I thought that the language barrier was going to be too much to overcome to be able to interact with the kids. I was so wrong. One little girl had me push her bicycle all around the courtyard and another played soccer with me. Language never seemed an issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;market&quot;&gt;Market&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2015/guatemala/market.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Picture of the market&quot; /&gt; 
At one point, I thought my local mall was big. Then, I saw the Guatemalan market. It’s a mixture of open air booths, fabric covered stalls, cement buildings, and wandering merchants. It’s what I imagine an Arabian bazzar would be like. Everything was for sale - bootleg movies, fresh produce, socks, dishwashers, toothpaste, massages, restaurant food, and even painted livestock (or rather, a pink chick). It seemed to go on for miles - a couple of us spent a solid 45 minutes and never encountered the same booth twice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;macadamia-nut-farm&quot;&gt;Macadamia Nut Farm&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2015/guatemala/macadamia.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;There's no nuts here...&quot; /&gt;
It turns out that macadamia nuts are farmed from trees. News to me too. We visited a small macadamia nut farm, where they grow hundreds of different varieties of macadamic nuts. Again, I thought there was one type (those that go inside cookies with white chocolate). They showed us the machinery they designed to individually process the nuts and fed us delicious pancakes. Everything was homemade and grown on the farm. This was down to the blueberries on the pancakes and the chocolate I bought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;volcano&quot;&gt;Volcano&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2015/guatemala/volcano.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Yes, there's a volcano. But, there's also a dog.&quot; /&gt;
Guatemala has at least thirty volcanoes throughout the country. In fact, an enormous volcano -suitable for any supervillian- dominated the southern skyline by our homestay. We took a whole day and hiked one of the local volancoes. The best parts were at the base. We roasted marshmallows over the heat emerging from the surface. That means we roasted them with no chance of charring them. Somebody, patent that please. There was also a cozy little store in a shack that sold souvenirs made from lava rock. I’ve never seen a business so far off the beaten path before.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 
 
 <entry>
   <title>Doctors</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/doctors/"/>
   <updated>2015-02-03T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/posts/doctors</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was ported from my old blog. It’s probably a mess.&lt;/em&gt;
It’s a rite of passge for teenagers to be cajoled by their parents into considering medicine as a career. It’s a pretty solid argument from their point of view. You get to be a young George Clooney, running around and saving lives with a healthy paycheck. They get to brag that “My child saves lives,” and throw around the d-word over dinner parties. Seems like a win-win, right? (Just remember, it’s all aabout the parents.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve spent a little too much time lately in hospitals. Nothing serious at all, promise. But, amongst all of the reasons I can think of to not go into medicine, I think hospitals alone are the reason I could never become a doctor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Waiting Music
For such calm music, it’s surprisingly aggressive. If somebody keeps telling you to calm down, it’s more agitating than anything.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PA System
I don’t know what a Code Blue is, but there was at least four of them throughout the day. Downtown Detroit may be undergoing quarantine. I really don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Local Anathestic
Surgery isn’t fun. Especially when you have to be awake during it. Local anathestic simplifies surgeries immensely and I’m grateful for it. But, it’s terrifying when you have to lay down on a table below the lights of heaven. You’re completely aware of every move that the surgeon is making and you just have to run with it. The actual process of surgery is something that only surgeons want to know the details of - hence the reason they went to medical school. I don’t want to know about where the incesion is going to be. I just want to be watching Netflix after it’s all done.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Paperwork
I’ve seen smaller textbooks than the paperwork necessary to walk into a waiting room. I may have adopted a child overseas and altered my will while trying to get to my follow-up appointment.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fluorescent Lighting
It’s affordable. That’s great for the bottom-line. It also induces migraines and flashbacks to sci-fi horror movies.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 
 
 <entry>
   <title>Hackathons</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/hackathons_good/"/>
   <updated>2015-01-18T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/posts/hackathons_good</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was ported from my old blog. It’s probably a mess&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;i-dont-hackathon-that-much-but-when-i-do-hackathon-i-always-go-to-mhacks&quot;&gt;I don’t hackathon that much. But when I do hackathon, I always go to MHacks.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re about 20 hours in so far. Or rather we’ve got 11:16 left according to MHacks app. Math isn’t exactly my friend at this point of the night. I’m not exactly sure what a number is anymore (but I definitely know what an int or float is.)  It’s always a wonder why people choose to abuse themselves through hackathons. If you code in class, why would you possibly spend all weekend doing it with no sleep and nothing but catered food and cookies? It’s something I’m pretty curious about right now, as I’m mentally exhausted, physically drained, and starring at my Facebook feed full of partying friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a huge frenzy around hackathons right now. I just counted a bazillion (10) Facebook groups without trying. There’s a major league in the vein of the MLB or the football people. People are running around in their pajamas with an IV of Red Bull, 3 different VR devices, and a combination of exhaustion and exhilaration. Some poor overworked recruiters are staying up all night to impress college students. It’s incredible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a bit of an outsider on the topic. I only go to my local hackathon, I never win and I usually bail out early. I’ve never gotten a job offer from one and my laptop doesn’t have four layers of startup stickers. Here are my thoughts - the thoughts from someone who isn’t convinced that hackathons are going to replace the world and everything in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-good&quot;&gt;The Good&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;companies&quot;&gt;Companies&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life isn’t all about the money and the jobs and the perks. Unless you ask Business Insider then (note to self: rant about bad journalism). But, it’s cool having all of these people try to woo you. It’s the closest to rock-star status I’ll ever have. Tons of free stuff. Hoodie pillows are apparently a thing. MHacks has a better “career fair” than the actual career fair. Even if you’re not looking, it’s still pretty fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;community&quot;&gt;Community&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m pretty bad about taking advantage of this. We have an office in the middle of the hackathon space. With a couch. Naturally, our team doesn’t ever leave that room. Our square-foot-per-person count is probably double digit. Insanity. But, it’s great to have so many people around. I’ve gotten into conversations about my Palantir jacket. There are students from all over the place. If I want help or  just a conversation, I can go pretty much anywhere. It is really cool how many like-minded people are put together and the power it brings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;motivation&quot;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel like there’s a very profound quote about mindsets, but it’s escaping me. It’s hard not to have a working mindset in the middle of a hackathon. If you didn’t try to work at all, you’d actually be pretty bored. Being trapped in a room full of programmers is a great way to learn to program. I’ve learned everything I know about mobile apps because of the fall MHacks. It was because I had the motiviation to sit down and figure it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-reservations&quot;&gt;The Reservations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;food&quot;&gt;Food&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, I’ve had some chicken, potatoes, veggies, pizza, and cookies. That’s the menu. Tomorrow will be Panera and bagels. It’s decent. But, it’s also incredibly unhealthy. I’m not the best eater on a good day, but even I think that this is a little much. I haven’t seen a piece of fruit all weekend. I’m dreaming (hallucinating) about Apples that don’t have batteries. Unhealthy food makes it a lot harder to stay alert over the weekend and it compounds the sleep deprivation pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;code&quot;&gt;Code&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hackathons encourage bad code. Move fast and break things, right? I’ve written terrible code this weekend. It’s riddled with errors. There’s misspellings. I’m not even sure if everything works. But, if I hit certain buttons in a certain order and pray really hard, things generally work. That’s a pretty bad practice. But, that’s what’s encouraged when I need a final “polished” product in 3 days. I’m painting a cardboard box to look like a car. Hope nobody tries to drive it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a quick note, I’d love to see prizes for the best pull request. Encourage people to write code that other people are going to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sleep&quot;&gt;Sleep&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a perception in America that hard work can solve anything. The gold diggers back in the turn of the century thought so - just dig more and you’ll find gold! But, it’s a flawed philosophy. There’s only so much a person can work. And it’s hardly healthy. I feel like hackathons perpetrate the overworking. Nobody here has gotten more than 5 hours of sleep this weekend. If I get 5 hours in one night, that was a bad night. And this is over a weekend - 3 days. Are we really expecting this from people in the real world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;im-gonna-be-prom-king-anymore&quot;&gt;I’m Gonna be Prom King Anymore&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot of people who love hackathons. They have their “Hell yeahs!” and their laptop stickers and their war stories. I would never, and won’t take that away from them. Hackathon organizers do a great job and should be rewarded for the blood and tears that are visible in these events (metaphorically. Haven’t seen any blood so far).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, I don’t think hackathons are for everybody. They aren’t for me. When I look back at everything I’ll miss from college, I don’t think that hackathons will be something that I’ll reminisce about. I feel like hackathons are perpetrating a hacker culture that I don’t want to be a part of. I have no intentions of dropping out to dedicate my life to a startup. I don’t want to build a hack that uses Node and Angular and Oculus and Glass and Pebble and 3D printers attached to robot drones in space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, more importantly, I don’t want coding to consume my life. Coding culture doesn’t seem great for balance. I’m expected to be working long weeks and then go off and hack with no rest on the side. That’s the hacker culture to me - never stop coding ever. For some people, it works great. But, I think that balance is going to become key as programming becomes more finely ingrained into our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel like everyone is screaming about “disruption” and “innovation” and the newest trends. And the more screaming there is, the harder it is to be heard if you’re not agreeing with the crowd.  That’s the conversation about hackathons and hacking in general. I think there’s more to community though. I think there’s people out there who see programming as a career or a hobby - not as their livelihood. They want to learn and grow as programmers, but they only want to go so far. They aren’t intimidated by the learning curve, but they don’t see a purpose in following it all the way. I hope those people, myself included, can speak up more. Programming shouldn’t your life. And I feel like hackathons are one of the many forces that encourage differently.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 
 
</feed>